Overson Family Photograph Collection, 1840-1950s (bulk 1920s-1940s)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Overson Family Photograph Collection, 1840-1950s (bulk 1920s-1940s)
MS 549
Overson, Margaret Jarvis, 1878-1968.
Photographs and negatives, primarily prints, glass plate, nitrate, and acetate negatives, but also a few travel stereographs, cabinet cards, cartes-de-visite, and daguerreotypes, mostly relating to the Overson family of St. Johns, Arizona, along with some of townspeople, buildings, and special occasions. There are a few portraits of people taken by Charles Jarvis, circa 1890 to 1910. More were taken by his daughter, Margaret Jarvis Overson, circa 1920 to 1960. A small amount were taken by other photographers and by her adult children, especially Eva M. Overson Tanner. The images include mostly unidentified people, family, student class groups, school athletic teams, and a few celebrations and street scenes. Photographs also include Mormon schools, school groups, church groups and church leaders.
14 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Charles Godfrey (DeFriez) Jarvis (1855-1919) settled in St. Johns, Arizona in the 1880s and operated a drug store where he also was a dentist, photographer, postmaster, notary public, and U.S. Land Commissioner, and had the first telephone office. He was born to the DeFriez family but was taken in by the Jarvis family and took their name. He married Margaret Jarvis (1857-1934) and they had eight children including Margaret Godfrey Jarvis (1878-1968).
Margaret Godfrey Jarvis assisted her father with photography beginning in her teens. She married Henry C. Overson (1968-1947) in 1896 and they had nine children: Eva M., Henry Victor, Albert N., Edgar P., Harry J., Evan, Ivan, Ross W., and Marion Peter. Henry Overson's construction company built and repaired houses and other buildings in St. Johns. Margaret continued her father's photography work from their home and on location.
The Jarvis and Overson families were members of the Church of Latter Day Saints accompanying many other settlers to St. Johns, Arizona in the early 1880s.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 2 series by type of material.
Series I: Photographs, 1840-1950s bulk 1920s-1940s
Series II: Negatives, circa 1890s-1940s
Subseries 1: Glass plate negatives, 5"x7", circa 1890-1930
Subseries 2: Glass plate negatives, 3"x4", circa 1890-1930
Subseries 3: Negatives, 4"x5", circa 1920s-1940s
Subseries 4: Negatives, 5"x7", circa 1920s-1940s
Scope and Content Note
Photographs and negatives relating mostly to the Overson family of St. Johns, Arizona but also from Charles Jarvis and later Margaret Overson's photography business in St. Johns. The images include Overson and related family members, Mormon groups, student class groups, high school sports teams, and a few St. Johns celebrations and street scenes.
Photographs known to be taken by Charles Jarvis consist of a small number of cabinet cards with his studio imprint. These are all studio portraits of individuals, children, and families, taken circa 1890 to 1910, and most appear to be family members although they are unidentified. There are a few school group and church group images probably taken during the late 1890s and forward.
Except for family photographs of Overson children and their activities, most of the collection represents the 1920s to 1940s, a time when Margaret's children were in high school and then marrying and starting their own families. Most of these images are of unidentified family members, and a smaller amount are unidentified portraits of others.
There are also some images of school buildings and students including high school sports teams, bands, drama productions, and graduating classes, mostly from the late 1910s to the late 1930s. Also present are a few images of Mormon church leaders and church groups, women's groups, and a boy scout camping trip (ca. 1930s).
Other highlights include a few images of parades and parade floats, celebrations, cart races at the 1937 Golden Jubilee Parade, and Henry Victor Overson dressed as "Uncle Sam" for a holiday. Other views of rural life include hay harvests, picnics and excursions, building construction, women's gatherings, and home interiors. One image shows a large meterorite on a flat-bed railroad car.
The images are mostly unidentified but some information can be taken from the content, from published histories of St. Johns, and from Margaret J. Overson's published family history which reproduced some of the images. All the images were scanned and are available in digital format. There is a good amount of duplication in the digital scans because images were sometimes scanned as negatives and then as prints, and each print was scanned even if it was a duplicate.
See the spreadsheet for the Overson Family Photographs for more specific information. Please contact an archivist to view spreadsheet.
Overson, Margaret Jarvis, Photographer.; Jarvis, Charles Godfrey, Photographer.; Automobiles -- Arizona -- Pictorial works.; Boy Scouts -- Arizona -- Pictorial works.; Building sites -– Arizona -- Saint Johns -- Pictorial works.; Camping -- Arizona -- Pictorial works.; Cartes-de-visite.; Children -- Pictorial works.; Daguerreotypes.; Dams -- Arizona -- Design and construction -- Pictorial works.; Domestic life -- Pictorial works.; Infants -- Pictorial works.; Jarvis family.; Meteorites -– Arizona -- Pictorial works.; Mormons -- Arizona -- Saint Johns -- Pictorial works.; Overson family.; Parades –- Arizona -- Saint Johns -- Pictorial works.; Photographers -- Arizona.; Photoprints.; Rural women -- Arizona -- Saint Johns -- Pictorial works.; School children -– Arizona -- Saint Johns -- Pictorial works.; Schools –- Arizona –- Saint Johns -- Pictorial works.; Sports teams -- Pictorial works.; Stereographs.; Tanner family.; Saint Johns, Ariz. -- Pictorial works.
Container List
- Series I: Photographs, 1840-1950s; bulk 1920s-1940s
  This series is arranged topically.
  - Overson, Eva Margaret, studio portraits, 1897-1920s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Overson, Eva, family and activities, 1910s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Overson, Eva - LeRoy Tanner (husband), 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Overson, Evan and Ivan, 1910s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Overson, Harry James, 1920s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Overson, Henry Christian, 1880s-1910s, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Overson, Margaret Godfrey Jarvis, 1890s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Overson, Henry C. and Margaret J., 1920s, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Overson, Henry Victor, studio portraits, 1900s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Overson, Henry V., family and activities, 1920s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Overson, Marion Peter, 1920s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Overson, Ross Wallace, 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Overson children (groups), including Victor as Uncle Sam, 1900s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Overson children (unidentified), 1900s-1930s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Tanner, Wallace Ove and Lee Henry, 1920s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Overson family groups, 1920s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Overson family homes, 1900s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Oveson family, Lars, Peter and Ove (correct spelling for earlier generation), 1880s-1920s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Oveson, Ove Christian and Mary K. Christiansen and children (correct spelling for earlier generation), 1888-1920 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Overson, David and Annie (Jarvis) and children, 1890-1910s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Overson, George Conrad, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Overson, Ove Ephraim, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Overson -- Miscellaneous identified -- (Carol, Merrill Lyman), 1900-1940s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Godfrey-Jarvis family, 1860s-1880s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Jarvis, George and Ann Prior, 1860s-1911 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Jarvis, Charles and Margaret and children, 1880s-1920s (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Portraits –- Identified, A-E (Anderson, Burk, Bigelow, Davis, Christiansen), 1880s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Portraits –- Identified, F-L (Greer, Hamblin, Knowles, Heap, Farr, Gibbons), 1890s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Portrait –- Hunt, George W.P. (FILED IN BOX 8), 1914 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Portraits –- Identified, M-R (Rogers, Mineer, Pace, Rencher, Pena, Noakes, Milne, McFate, Morgan, Pulsipher, Pershing), 1890s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Portraits –- Webb, William, Jr. and family, 1890s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Portraits –- Identified, S-Z (Shumway, White, Whiting, Sherwood, Tenney, Wilkins, Richey, Dora Sherwood Udall), 1890s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cartes-de-visite, Men, women, children, families, including Paul Paulson (Photographers: C.R. Savage, Dagmar N. Jonstrup, G.F. Anderson, Crocwell and Ottinger), 1870s-1880s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Portraits –- Children, unidentified, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Portraits –- Children, unidentified, 1900s-1920s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Portraits –- Children, unidentified, 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Portraits –- Children, First communion/confirmation, 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Portraits –- Couples, unidentified, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Portraits –- Couples, unidentified, 1900s-1920s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Portraits –- Couples, unidentified, 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Portraits –- Wedding couples, unidentified, 1890s-1920s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Portraits –- Wedding couples, unidentified, 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Portraits –- Wedding groups, unidentified, 1920s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Portraits –- Families –- reprints, unidentified, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Portraits –- Families –- cabinet cards, unidentified, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Portraits –- Families –- studio portraits, unidentified, 1900s-1920s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Portraits –- Families –- outdoors, unidentified, 1900s-1920s (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Portraits –- Families, unidentified (1 of 2), 1930s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Portraits –- Families, unidentified (2 of 2), 1930s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Portraits –- Families, fireplace background, unidentified, 1930s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Portraits –- Men, unidentified, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Portraits –- Men, studio portraits, unidentified (1 of 2), 1900s-1920s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Portraits –- Men, studio portraits, unidentified (2 of 2), 1900s-1920s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Portraits –- Men, outdoors and small prints, unidentified, 1900s-1920s (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Portraits –- Men, older men, unidentified, 1930s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Portraits –- Men, younger men, unidentified, 1930s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Portraits –- Men, portraits in folders, unidentified, 1930s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Portraits -– Men, in uniform, unidentified, 1910s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Portraits –- Women, unidentified, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Portraits -– Women, unidentified (1 of 2), 1900s-1910s (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Portraits -– Women, unidentified (2 of 2), 1900s-1910s (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Portraits –- Women, portraits in folders (1 of 2), 1900s-1920s (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Portraits –- Women, portraits in folders (2 of 2), 1900s-1920s (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Portraits –- Women, unidentified (1 of 2), 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Portraits –- Women, unidentified (2 of 2), 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Portraits -– Women, portraits in folders, 1930s-1940s (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Portraits –- Women, studio portraits (1 of 2), 1940s-1950s (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Portraits –- Women, studio portraits (2 of 2), 1940s-1950s (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Portraits -– Women, small images and outdoors, 1940s-1950s (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Portraits –- Women, copy prints, 1920s-1940s (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Portraits, group, unidentified, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Portraits, group, unidentified, 1900s-1920s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Portraits, group, unidentified, 1930s-1940s (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Portraits, group –- Mormon church groups, 1910s, 1940s (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Portraits, group –- Students-Band, orchestra and theater, 1900s-1940s (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Portraits, group –- Students, 1900s-1920s (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Portraits, group –- Students, 1930s-1940s (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Portraits, group –- Students, sports teams, 1910s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Portraits, group –- Students, sports, mounted, 1910-1930s (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Portraits, multiple images/copy prints, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Subjects –- Adults and children with animals, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Subjects –- Scouts and camping, 1920s-1940s (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Subjects –- Firearms, hunting and fishing, 1910s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Subjects –- Picnics, etc., 1900s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Subjects -– Transportation, 1910s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Subjects -– Work, 1910s-1940s (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Subjects –- Meteorite "Navajo", June 16, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Places –- St. Johns, 1910s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Places –- St. Johns -– Celebrations, 1910s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Places –- St. Johns –- Celebrations -– World War I soldiers "welcome home" parade, 1918-1919 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Places –- St. Johns and unidentified -– Businesses, 1910s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Places -– St. Johns and unidentified -– Homes, 1890s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Places -– St. Johns and unidentified –- Buildings, 1900s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Places –- Dams, lakes, rivers and bridges, 1890s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Places –- Scenic views, 1910s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Places -– Scenic postcards, 1930s-1950s (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Places –- Travel, 1910s-1940s (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Stereographs -– Travel, etc., 1898-1904 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Album pages, small, 1915-1920s (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Album pages, loose photos (1 of 2), 1915-1920s (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Album pages, loose photos (2 of 2), 1915-1920s (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Album pages, loose photos, girls excursion, 1915-1920s (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Large album pages, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous snapshots, 1910s-1940s (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Mother and casket, the Pledgers, cemetery, garden, cakes), 1910s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Documents, photos of, 1842 and undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Envelopes and notes, 1920s-1940s (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Wooden box with glass (photographic equipment), undated (Box 8)
- Series II: Negatives, circa 1890s-1940s
  - Subseries 1: Glass plate negatives, 5"x7", circa 1890-1930
    This series is arranged by the date of scanning and assigned number.
    For example: 2012 0311-169 was scanned on 03-11-2012 and numbered 169 during scanning. See an archivist regarding access to the digitized versions.
    - 2012 0311_169 to 0311_194 (Box 9)
    - 2012 0311_195 to 0311_220 (Box 10)
    - 2012 0311_221 to 0311_223; 2012 0427_0001 to 0427_0023 (Box 11)
    - 2012 0427_0024 to 0427_0034; 2012 0505_0360 to 0505_0373 (Box 12)
    - 2012 0505_0374 to 0505_0399 (Box 13)
    - 2012 0701_0955 to 0701_0979 (Box 14)
    - 2012 0701_0980 to 0701_1004 (Box 15)
    - 2012 0701_1005 to 0701_1030 (Box 16)
    - 2012 0701_1031 to 0701_1048; 2012 1007_1 to 1007_15 (Box 17)
    - 2012 1007_17 to 1007_63 (Box 18)
    - 2012 1021_1807 to 1021_1831 (Box 19)
    - 2012 1021_1832 to 1021_1856 (Box 20)
    - 2012 1021_1857 to 1021_1866, with 5 oversize plates: 2013 0120_30, 2013 0120_62, 2012 0427_0017, 2012 0701_1029 plat map, Plat map 1888 no ID number, 2012-2013 (Box 21)
  - Subseries 2: Glass plate negatives, 3"x4", circa 1890-1930
    For example: 2012 0311-169 was scanned on 03-11-2012 and numbered 169 during scanning.
    - 2012 0318_0224P to 0408_0225 (Box 22)
    - 2012 0408_0256 to 0408_0285 (Box 23)
    - 2012 0408_0286 to 0415_0320 (Box 24)
    - 2012 0415_0321 to 0415_0355 (Box 25)
    - 2012 0415_0356 to 0415_0359 (also 2 very broken plates, 2 not scanned) (Box 26)
  - Subseries 3: Negatives, 4"x5", circa 1920s-1940s
    - 2012 0506_0035 to 0617_0806 (Box 27)
    - 2012 0617_0811 to 1021_1618 (Box 28)
    - 2012 1021_1621 to 2013 0101_068 (Box 29)
    - 2013 0101_069 to 0127_101 (Box 30)
  - Subseries 4: Negatives, 5"x7", circa 1920s-1940s
    - 2012 0512_various numbers; 0152-0154, 0158, 0519-0523, 0740, 790-0792, 0795-1730; 2012 12-02_1tb; 2013 01-27_083, 2012-2013 (Box 31)